Software Engineering Radio episode 6
Model Driven Software Development part
two.
This is the second part of our
introduction to Model Driven Software
Development. In the first episode on
this topic we talked about what Model
Driven Development is all about
about the core concepts about the
tooling about some of the MDA standard.
In this episode we'll talk more about
the soft topics like how do you
introduce MDSD into projects? How do you
make sure all your all your developers
can understand the technology? How do
you combine MDSD with Agile Development?
Have fun.
So with all these metamodels and
metametamodels and models and whatever
I'm wondering whether you
what this means for the kind of
programmer that you need to have in your
projects. So is it possible to do this
on your own? Do you need to have some
kind of super programmers that know
everything about EMF and UML and the UML
tool and metamodels and metamodel
transformations and what have you? Well,
of course using Model Driven Development
is is a shift from traditional
development. Not just because you have
to know and understand
all those passwords.
Also because you know, not all projects
think well and extensively about their
architecture. So being forced to make
that explicit is also a problem.
Of course you have to learn all those
tools and some of the concepts.
And of course if you start a project
it's probably not good to start a new
project in a new domain with a new
technology and a new platform and then
also introducing MDSD because that would
be too much.
So when
starting to use MDSD you should do this
in a familiar environment with your you
know, you've used J2EE for five projects
and you use it again and now you use the
automation provided by MDSD. So this is
the first important thing. Second thing
is that there are two different roles
in MDSD based projects. The first role
is actually those folks who
you know, formalize the architecture and
build the generator define the
metamodels.
This is what we call the domain
architecture development track or threat
or path. And then there is the other
group of people who use
who use this um
generator to
yeah, build applications. And those
people don't have to understand all
those fancy things. They just have to be
able to draw or write up models and then
start generator and know how to work
with what the generator spits out. And
of course
that might be non-trivial. So you have
to document the programming model and
how to use the generator, how to use the
DSL. But this rather magic stuff
you know, one or two meta levels higher
that's something only a limited group of
people should usually use. Also my
experience is that
being able to formalize things into
metamodels and working on that
conceptual level is not everybody's
not everybody can easily do that. It's
it's to some extent you you can learn it
but not completely. There has to be you
know, some kind of predisposition for
people
being able to do that. So there are some
folks in projects who usually like doing
that. I mean of course you have to make
sure that they you know, don't start you
know, drifting off and and coming up
with rather cool generators that don't
solve anybody's problem. But you have to
make sure that you have those two
different groups of people. For the
people who who like doing that and who
kind of want to do that in projects
these people understand it reasonably
well fast. On the other hand I think and
that's not I'm not saying that because I
I want to sell consulting hours or
anything. It's my experience is really
that it helps at the beginning of a
project to have somebody that has done
it before giving you some advice
avoiding the basic pitfalls and maybe
also showing you how to work with the
tool you want to use. So that because it
is new in several respects it it does
make sense to have somebody help you.
So that's basically something that that
you can say for everything that you have
to introduce new into an organization
that you have to have somebody that is
experienced and external help can help
and so on and so on. So that's probably
not so
so surprising. The other thing that I'm
wondering is at the end of the day we
are talking about automation and usually
this means that you generate a payoff
after doing the same thing several
times. So usually you would expect that
you would have to do a significant
investment into automation and you get a
payoff after some projects that benefit
from the automation to do less manual
work.
So what I'm wondering is how many
projects do I have to have
of the same kind until my generator and
my investment into automation
pays off? Can you give any
hints about this from your experience?
So of course in in in the case of MDSD
the economies of scale hit you hard.
That means if you build an
infrastructure
you know, metamodels generators and
stuff that you can use over and over and
over and over again then this is
obviously an advantage. So if you work
in software system families where
product lines where
you build all kinds of applications
based on the same domain architecture
then this is an advantage obviously and
it's probably easy to argue that in such
a setting it's good to use the approach
we just talked about. So the challenge
is how do I make sure that using MDSD
already pays off much earlier and not
only you know, after in three years
because almost nobody invests into
something that pays off after three
years.
So what I always say and the funny thing
is that all the people I know who have
really experience in MDSD they will say
exactly the same.
If
introducing MDSD doesn't pay off in the
first project you did something wrong.
So
you have to do it pragmatically of
course. You can't you shouldn't try to
aim at the holy grail of real domain
specific stuff as we talked about
before. But if you automate your
architecture
um sensibly then this can save you so
much work that this pays off after a
couple of weeks or months. Of course
there is one precondition if you count
in
learning all the tools
into one project then that might not be
true. But if you have some external help
for a week or two and they set you up
the basic infrastructure and teach you
some best practices and some
anti-patterns then I would say that in a
project you know, like seven or eight
people working for a couple of months
using MDSD will pay off. This is
definitely my experience and
it's not just about you know, spending
less work coming you know, spitting out
the code. It's also your your your
software quality improves because
generators don't make accidental errors.
They're either always right or always
wrong and things that are always wrong
can more easily be debugged than things
that are only are only occasionally
wrong. And also you can more easily
change the platform. If you want to
migrate for example from Hibernate to
TopLink then this is rather easy because
if you didn't do things completely wrong
then you just have to adapt your code
generation templates. So what I'm saying
is that in addition to spending less
effort and doing
you know, having less work to do you
also improve maintainability and
software quality and and also you you
kind of capture best practices about
about your architecture in in in in
templates and metamodels. So there are
all kinds of kind of non-countable
benefits that are really important and
so
if if you take that into account it it
pays off really early. So the the thing
to note here is it's not just about
automation it's also about architecture
centric
architecture centric view and how this
improves software development in
general.
So
and and also the the effort at least
from what I've seen
to implement such a generator is not as
big as you would probably think when
when you hear about that.
Right. So to today's tools are
I wouldn't say sophisticated because
compared to you know, mainstream IDEs
like Eclipse it's still quite in its
infancy. But those tools are really not
too bad and you can work productively
with them and so getting into those
tools is not as bad as it might look if
you look from the outside. So is this
the weapon that we've been looking for
to fight offshoring or is it not enough
to get this payoff to keep programming
jobs in Europe or the US?
Yeah, this is an interesting topic. I
mean
why will people offshore things?
One thing is because of political
reasons. Some you know, boss CEO or C
whatever O decided that strategically
50% of all development effort has to be
outsourced or offshore to some wherever.
So I can't argue against that. That's
political strategic I mean not my
problem. What I can say is that if you
want if you think about offshoring
because you have a real reason for it
which means that you can have a lot of
work being done for less money
then using MDSD can be an alternative
and and that is in two ways. First of
all, if you automate then the brain dead
work that you are probably inclined to
out offshore is it doesn't happen
anymore because the generator does that
for you. So, you know, you don't have
those large amounts of stupid things
that people have to do over and over and
over and over again and that's too
expensive and therefore you have to
offshore it. So, that's that's one
argument
which is against offshoring and pro
MDSD, of course.
The other thing is that if you have to
offshore, then the challenge is to off
to the offshore in a way that the core
know-how about your architecture and
your stays in-house. You don't want to
offshore your knowledge. You want to
offshore work.
And if you do that, you can use MDSD to
ensure that. So, you can you can for
example define the architecture and the
generators locally
and define a programming model that is
well restricted by using generators and
all kinds of things, patterns, and
stuff. And then you can let people do
the the implementation of the business
logic uh somewhere else. So, you could
uh for example come up with uh some
specifications using your DSLs locally
and then ship that over to uh the
offshore location where people then
add some of the business logic and maybe
draw the GUIs which are often hard to
generate if you want it um
to look really nice. Um so, there are
other means by which MDSD can help make
offshoring more feasible. However, to be
honest, I think if you do MDSD right,
you don't want to offshore.
And and do you think it's important that
um
that you reach the holy grail of doing
MDSD uh with real domain specific
language to
uh to to uh be able to compete against
offshoring or is it already enough to
have this architecture centric uh MDSD
approach?
It really depends um
what you want to achieve with
offshoring. If it's really that you want
to have those huge amounts of work being
done cheaper, then you can automate
large part of that and you wouldn't want
to uh offshore anymore. Um
So, actually I'm to be honest, I don't
really I don't know. I mean, I if I had
to decide between offshoring and model
driven,
uh obviously I would use model driven
and that's also because you know those
risks of communication and different
cultures and time zones and all that
stuff. That's not there. Of course, you
have risks too if you go to this new
MDSD technology, but it's it's something
that's a bit more controlled. Now, of
course, on the other side I had I have
to say that I have more experience with
MDSD than with offshoring. So, maybe I'm
not quite quite fair here, but to me it
seems that automating things is better
than getting huge amounts of people to
do cheap work because, you know, they
all have to be coordinated and managed
and all these things. So, I'm I'm I'm
really skeptical about the offshoring
thing.
An interesting idea to have MDSD to
solve part of the communication problem
that you already or those have in
software development projects because
there are these people that have to be
coordinated and so on. So, one other
thing that I'm wondering is I mean, the
role of the model is um
is pretty much a formalized model and
it's uh becoming a software artifact and
that's quite different from what for
example agility says because agility
says, "Okay, so models are one part of
communication and it's something that I
draw somewhere on a whiteboard or
whatever and if everybody says, "Okay,
this is what we agree upon and we all
know what this means and it aids us in
communication." That's what we want from
the models and that's pretty much
different from what MDSD says because it
says, "Okay, this has to be formalized
and it's one of part of the code that we
are going to produce." And so on. So, do
you think that
the you can actually use MDSD in an
Agile project? I have never used MDSD in
any other context than in Agile project.
So,
I'm not sure if this this discussion
between Agile and model driven is still
so important today. Two or three years
ago it was important because it was kind
of, you know, "Oh, the case tool folks
come back and now they're calling it
MDSD and we don't want that." I think
those two approaches don't contradict
each other at all.
Um I'm going as far as to say that you
can't be Agile without being model
driven. Now, that's probably too far,
but um what I'm trying to say is that if
you do MDSD right, then it helps you to
become more Agile. Examples, um
if you want to migrate your project,
your code from one technical
infrastructure to another, for example,
to a new version of J2EE or something,
then using model driven development,
this is much easier because you only
have to change things in one place,
templates, code generation templates.
So, this makes you more Agile because
you can respond to change in technical
aspects more quickly. The same is true
to uh for
functional non-technical things. Like if
your customer has different algorithms,
different different
you know, attributes for your entities,
different
uh GUI layout,
you can just change things in one place
again, which is in this case the model,
and then regenerate the application. So,
this also makes you more Agile.
Another thing is if you have a good DSL
that represents your domain concepts
nicely, then it becomes feasible to do
pair programming with domain experts.
I'm not saying that, you know, DSLs are
so good that your customer can do the
programming for you. That's probably an
illusion. But you can actually uh sit
together in front of a machine. You have
your domain expert. You have your um
programmer who uses your DSLs to build
models.
And then if the domain expert wants
something different, has a different
requirement, you change things, press a
button, and a couple of minutes later,
depending how long your generator runs,
you have a running application. So, this
this um customer integration can be can
be improved significantly. Another thing
is that if you talk to many of the Agile
folks, then they're really big fans of
automating all kinds of things. They
want automated tests. They want
automated build. They want automated
creation of documentation, at least
JavaDoc and these kinds of things. So,
using automation to generate some of the
code and to, you know, do some of the
tedious work is just a logical
consequence. It's just the next step.
So, I don't think there is any
difference in mindset here. So, I think
MDSD and Agile development go together
really well. Now, of course, there is
Oh, yeah, testing. Um
many people um
equal Agile development with test
driven. And of course, you can do the
same in model driven development. You
can first, for example,
um come up with your component
structures in a model. You generate the
interfaces. Then you write a test case.
And then you implement your business
logic uh until the test shows green. So,
you can do this approach in exactly the
same way as as before. Now, there are
two things that that is that is
important to say that things work. One
is domain architectures like those DSLs
and metamodels, they're built on
experience. We don't want to come up
with a big design up front where there
is a magic team of architects that sits
into a room for half a year, comes up
with the architecture and the generator
and then people have to use it no matter
whether it really solves anybody's
problem. So, it's really really really
really really important to build those
meta artifacts, the domain architecture
as you go in the project. And that also
means that you have to have people on
the project who are able and good enough
and fast enough to respond to changes or
to to implement changes in the domain
architecture. So, if the application
developers tell you the generator is
missing a feature or something doesn't
work and something is wrong and the
architecture doesn't work, then you have
to be able to change these things and
not, you know, within 6 weeks because
then your application developers get
frustrated and you're screwed. So, what
you have to do is to make sure you have
a team of people who can respond to
changes in requirements with regards to
the domain architecture quickly. And
that is that is the real challenge in
model driven development, to coordinate
the domain architecture development with
application development because
application development is driven by
short-term goals and deadlines by the
customer and you know, we need this
feature tomorrow otherwise the
customer's gone. Whereas the domain
architecture development has more this,
you know, mid-term thing. You want to
build an infrastructure you can reuse.
You want to do the architecture right.
You want to make sure things are clean
and nice. So, aligning those two goals
and also making compromises in both
domains from time to time and then maybe
fixing them later. Like you have to do
some hack in the generator to make
application developers happy, but then
in the next iteration, you um you fix
the generator and do it nicely.
That's the real challenge. And doing
that iteratively in in for example, you
know, a new generator release every week
and then also make sure that the
generator knows about the different
model versions and can handle these
things. That is non-trivial and that is
also where experience is required. Come
you know, understanding those tools and
building nice DSLs is not that
complicated, but making that work in
like projects with more than five
people, that's certainly a challenge.
It's comparable to building frameworks.
And we all know that if you don't manage
that carefully, you get really cool
frameworks that nobody needs.
Yeah, so I think um that was quite a lot
of really interesting experiences and
explanations about MDSD and models and
model driven approaches and so on. And
I think it's really a good idea to take
a look at this yourself and try to
figure out how it could work for you.
And uh there are some
um
some links on our home on our homepage
which is http um
se-radio.net.
So, one thing I want to add at at the at
the end. So, two things. First of all,
try it. It's First of all, it's fun.
And second, it's much easier than you
might think. And the second thing is
that uh we we just scratched the surface
in this episode, and we will probably
have additional episodes on this topic
down the road. Not the next subsequent
ones, but from time to time we'll catch
up this topic again and again. And uh
one thing we might certainly will take a
look at is, for example, doing, you
know, discussing things a bit more
practical. Like, you know, what tools do
you use? What specific steps have do you
have to do to do it? Where is a good
starting point? And these kinds of
things. So, we'll we'll do that in
subsequent appro- episodes. This one was
thought as laying the foundation for
this topic. And I think
um talking about Software Engineering
Radio in general, we'll have, over time,
we'll have several threads probably,
which we'll wrap again and again and and
and you know, provide more and more
details over time.
So, um
that's it.
Yeah. Okay, so thanks for listening.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio. For general
information, feedback, and past
episodes, go to se-radio.net.
Software Engineering Radio wants to
thank Henning Pawly for providing the
music we use in this show.